<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="yes" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc colonspace="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-jennings-vipr-overview-06"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="VIPR Overview">Verification Involving PSTN Reachability:
    Requirements and Architecture Overview</title>

    <author fullname="Mary Barnes" initials="M." surname="Barnes, Ed.">
      <organization>Polycom</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region>TX</region>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mary.ietf.barnes@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    
    
    
    <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <street>MS: SJC-21/2</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 421-9990</phone>

        <email>fluffy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jonathan Rosenberg" initials="J.R." surname="Rosenberg">
      <organization>jdrosen.net</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Monmouth</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jdrosen@jdrosen.net</email>

        <uri>http://www.jdrosen.net</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    
    <author fullname="Marc Petit-Huguenin" initials="M."
            surname="Petit-Huguenin">
      <organization>Unaffiliated</organization>

      <address>
        <email>petithug@acm.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date month="December" day="9" year="2013" />

    <area>RAI</area>

    <workgroup>VIPR WG</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) has seen widespread deployment
      within individual domains, typically supporting voice and video
      communications. Though it was designed from the outset to support
      inter-domain federation over the public Internet, such federation has
      not materialized. The primary reasons for this are the complexities of
      inter-domain phone number routing and concerns over security. This
      document reviews this problem space, outlines requirements, and then
      describes a  model and technique for inter-domain federation with
      SIP involving the Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN), 
      called Verification Involving PSTN Reachability (VIPR). VIPR
      addresses the problems that have prevented inter-domain federation over
      the Internet. It provides fully distributed inter-domain routing for
      phone numbers, authorized mappings from phone numbers to domains, a new
      technique for automated SIP anti-spam, and privacy of number ownership,
      all while preserving the trapezoidal model of SIP.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Session Initiation Protocol (SIP) was originally published as
      <xref target="RFC2543" /> in May of 1999. This was followed
      by subsequent publication of <xref target="RFC3261"/>,
      which brought the protocol to sufficient maturity to enable large scale
      market adoption.</t>

      <t>
      SIP has achieved large scale market adoption with 
      hundreds of implementations, spanning consumer products, enterprise
      servers, and large scale carrier equipment. It carries billions and
      billions of minutes of calls, and has become the standard for
      interconnection between products from different vendors. If one measures
      success in deployment, then clearly SIP is a success.</t>

      <t> SIP was designed from the
      ground up to enable communications between users in different domains,
      all over the public Internet. The intention was that real-time
      communications should be no different than email or the web, with the
      same any-to-any connectivity that has fueled the successes of those
      technologies. 
      However, when SIP is used between domains, it is typically 
      through private federation agreements.  While such agreements are positive,
      they have typically been limited to voice,
       which has limited the use of video and the growth of advanced SIP features, 
       thus preventing
       the innovation that SIP was expected to drive.  Thus,
        the any-to-any Internet
      federation model envisioned by SIP has not materialized at scale.</t>

      <t>This document introduces a technology, called Verification
      Involving PSTN Reachability (VIPR), that breaks down the
      barriers that have prevented inter-domain voice, video and other multimedia
      services. By stepping back and
      changing some of the most fundamental assumptions about federation, VIPR
      is able to address the key problems preventing its deployment. VIPR
      focuses on incremental deployability. At
      the same time, VIPR ensures that SIP's trapezoidal model of direct
      federation between domains without any intermediate processing beyond IP
      transport is realized. That model is required in order to allow
      innovative new services to be deployed.</t>
	  
	  <t>Despite the advantages of the VIPR system, its open, peer-to-peer
	  character makes it vulnerable to certain security and privacy
	  vulnerabilities (see especially <xref target="malicious"/>). After
	  consideration of potential countermeasures, the VIPR working group
	  elected not to pursue VIPR for standardization.  This document
	  therefore describes VIPR for informational purposes, as VIPR has seen
	  some field deployment, and it is furthermore believed that the
	  techniques utilized by VIPR might be reused in new standard
	  architectures in the future.
	  </t>

    </section>
    
     <!-- Conventions  and Terminology -->
    
    <section anchor="sec:conventions" title="Conventions and Terminology">
    
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and 
        "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>. 
      </t>
		
	  <t>
		<list style="hanging">
		    <t hangText="Call Agent: ">
			An entity in a SIP enabled domain that supports VIPR.
			The Call Agent performs call processing on behalf
			of one or more user agents represented by E.164 numbers within the domain.        
			</t>
					
			<t hangText="Ticket: ">
			A shared secret that is generated after a PSTN call to enable secure call setup 
			on a subsequent inter-domain IP call enabled by VIPR.  
			</t>
			
            <t hangText="User Agent: ">
			As defined in <xref target="RFC3261"/>, with the restriction that the user agent
			must have an associated E.164 number. 
			</t>
	    </list>
	</t>  
      
    </section>
    <!--Terminology-->      
    

 <section title="Problem Statement">
      <t>The first question that must be asked is this - why haven't we seen
      widespread adoption of inter-domain SIP federation?
      The reason for this is due to problems with the following - summarized
      in order of importance/impact:</t>
      <t> 
      <list style="numbers">
      <t> Phone number routing </t>
      <t> Open pinhole </t>
      <t> Quality of service</t>
      <t> Troubleshooting</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t> The first two
      are the most significant.</t>
      
        <section anchor="phone-numbers" title="The Phone Number Routing Problem">
        <t> 
        Inter-domain federation requires that the sending domain determine
        the address of the receiving domain, in the form of a DNS name
        (example.com) or one or more IP addresses that can be used to reach
        the domain. In email and in the web, this is easy. The identifiers
        used by those services - the email address and web URL respectively -
        embed the address of the receiving domain. A simple DNS lookup is all
        that is required to route the connection. SIP was designed to use the
        same email-style identifiers.</t>
        
        <t>
        However, most SIP deployments utilize phone numbers in the form of E.164
        numbers <xref target="E.164"/>, and not
        email-style SIP URIs. This is due to the huge installed base of users
        that continue to exist solely on the PSTN. 
        In order to be reached by users on the PSTN, and in order to
        reach them, users in SIP deployments need to be assigned a PSTN phone
        number. 
        Users in SIP deployments need to place that phone number
        on business cards, use it in their email signatures, and in general,
        give it out to their friends and colleagues, in order to be reached.
        While those users could additionally have an email style SIP URI, the
        phone number serves as a single, global identifier that works for
        receiving calls from users on the PSTN as well as users within the
        same SIP domain.
        </t> 
        
        <t> There are several reasons why two identifiers are used when one
        will suffice. The
        universality of PSTN phone numbers is the reason why most SIP deployments
        continue to use them - often exclusively.</t>

        <t>Another reason is that many SIP deployments utilize hardphones or
        telephony adaptors, and the user interfaces on these devices -
        patterned after existing phones - only allow phone number based
        dialing. Consequently, these users are only allocated PSTN phone numbers,
        and not email-style SIP URI.</t>

        <t>Finally, a large number of SIP deployments are in domains where the
        endpoints are not IP. Rather, they are circuit based devices,
        connected to a SIP network through a gateway. SIP is used within the
        core of the network, providing lower cost transit, or providing add-on
        services. Clearly, in these deployments, only phone numbers are
        used.</t>

        <t>Consequently, to make inter-domain federation incrementally
        deployable and widely applicable, it needs to work with PSTN phone numbers
        rather than email-style SIP URIs. Telephone numbers, unlike email
        addresses, do not provide any indication of the address of the domain
        which "owns" the phone number. Indeed, the notion of phone number
        ownership is somewhat cloudy. Phone numbers can be ported between carriers.
        They can be assigned to a user or enterprise, and then later
        re-assigned to someone else. Phone numbers are granted to users and
        enterprises through a complex delegation process involving the ITU,
        governments, and telecommunications carriers, often involving local
        regulations that vary from country to country.</t>

        <t>Therefore, in order to deploy inter-domain federation, domains are
        required to utilize some kind of mechanism to map phone numbers to the
        address of the domain to which calls should be routed. Though several
        techniques have been developed to address this issue, none have
        achieved large-scale Internet deployments.</t>
      
        
      </section> 
      
                  
      <section anchor="pinhole" title="The Open Pinhole Problem">
        <t>The inter-domain federation mechanism built into SIP borrows
        heavily from email. Each domain runs a SIP server on an open port.
        When one domain wishes to contact another, it looks up the domain name
        in the DNS, and connects to that server on the open port. Here,
        "open" means that the server is reachable from anywhere on the public
        Internet, and is not blocked by firewalls.</t>

        <t>This simple design worked well in the early days of email. However, 
        the email system has now become plagued with spam. This has
        resulted in administrators spending a significant amount of time
        maintaining spam filters. This does not always benefit the end users
        as in some cases valid emails are dropped without the user being 
        notified.  Thus, administrators of SIP domains are rightfully concerned
        that if they make a SIP server available for anyone on the Internet to
        contact, it will open the floodgates for SIP spam, which is far more
        disruptive than email-based spam <xref target="RFC5039"></xref>.
        Administrators are also concerned that an open server will
        create a back-door for denial-of-service and other attacks that can
        potentially disrupt their voice and video services. Administrators are often not
        willing to take that risk since voice deployments
        demand higher uptimes and better levels of reliability than email,
        especially for enterprises.</t>

        <t>Fears around spam and denial-of-service attacks, when put together,
        form the "open pinhole problem" - that domains are not willing to
        enable SIP on an open port facing the Internet.</t>

        <t>To fix this, a new model for federation is needed - a model where
        these problems are addressed as part of the fundamental design rather than
        after the functionality has been deployed.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Quality of Service Problem">
        <t>The Internet does not provide any Quality of Service (QoS) guarantees. All traffic is
        best effort. This is not an issue for data transaction services, like
        web and email. It is, however, a concern when using real-time
        services, such as voice and video.</t>

        <t>That said, there are a large number of existing SIP deployments
        that run over the Internet. Though the lack of QoS is a concern, it
        has not proven a barrier to deployment.  It is believed that if
        if the more
        fundamental issues - the phone number routing and open pinhole
        problems - can be addressed, the QoS problem will be a non-issue. As
        such, QoS is not discussed further in this or other VIPR specifications.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Troubleshooting Problem">
        <t>The final problem that is prohibing large scale inter-domain
        federation is troubleshooting. When connecting calls
        between domains, problems can occur. Calls can be blocked. Calls
        can be misdelivered. Features sometimes don't work. There can be one-way
        media or no media at all. The video may not start. Call quality can be
        poor.</t>

        <t>These problems are common in SIP deployments, and they are tough
        to troubleshoot even within a single administrative domain. When
        real-time services extend inter-domain, the problem becomes worse.</t>

        <t>Fortunately, some work has been completed to improve the ability for network
        administrators to diagnose SIP problems. A Common log format <xref
        target="RFC6873"></xref> has been developed. 
        Other work underway, such as consistent session IDs <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-insipid-session-id-reqts"></xref> and 
        <xref target="I-D.jones-insipid-session-id"></xref> can help troubleshoot
        interdomain calls.</t>

        <t>In addition to the above, any new technology that facilitates
        inter-domain federation needs to have troubleshooting built-in, so
        that it is not a barrier to deployment. Further consideration of 
        necessary built-in techniques for troubleshooting is required for
        successful deployment of VIPR.</t>
      </section>
      
    </section>

    <section title="Summary of Existing Solutions">
      <t>Given the value of inter-domain SIP federation, there are 
      existing deployed solutions summarized below. However, each solution
      approach has
      fundamental limitations that have inhibited widespread deployment.</t>

      <section title="Domain Routing">
        <t>The first solution for SIP inter-domain
        federation is built into SIP itself - domain routing. In this
        technique, users utilize email-style SIP URIs as identifiers. By
        utilizing the DNS lookup mechanism defined in <xref
        target="RFC3263"></xref>, SIP enables calls to be routed between
        domains in much the same way email is routed between domains.</t>

        <t>This technique works well in theory, but it has two limitations
        which have limited its deployment:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>The majority of SIP deployments utilize phone numbers, often
            exclusively. In such a case, domain routing cannot be used.</t>

            <t>Domain federation brings with it the possibility (and strong
            likelihood) of the same levels of spam and DoS attacks that have
            plagued the email system.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>These issues have already been discussed in sections <xref target="phone-numbers"/> and 
        <xref target="pinhole"/> respectively.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Public ENUM">
        <t>Public ENUM, defined in <xref target="RFC6116"></xref> addresses
        the phone number routing problem by placing phone
        numbers into the public DNS. Clients can then perform a simple DNS
        lookup on a phone number, and retrieve a SIP URI which can be used to
        route to that phone number.</t>

        <t>Unfortunately, public ENUM requires that the entries placed into
        the DNS be populated following a chain of responsibility that mirrors
        the ownership of the numbers themselves. This means that, in order for
        a number to be placed into the DNS, authorization to do so must start
        with the ITU, and from there, move to the country, telecom regulator,
        and ultimately the end user. The number of layers of bureaucracy
        required to accomplish this is non-trivial. In addition, the telecom
        operators - that would be partly responsible for populating the
        numbers into the DNS - have little incentive to do so. As a
        consequence, public ENUM is largely empty, and is likely to remain so
        for the foreseeable future.</t>

        <t>Instead, ENUM has evolved into a technique for federation amongst
        closed peering partners, called private ENUM or infrastructure ENUM
        <xref target="RFC5067"></xref>. While there is value in this
        technology, it does not enable the open federation that public ENUM
        was designed to solve.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="Private Federations">
        <t>Private federations are a cooperative formed amongst a small number
        of participating domains. The cooperative agrees to use a common
        technique for federation, and through it, is able to connect to each
        other. There are many such federations in use today.</t>

        <t>Some of these federations rely on a central database, typically run
        by the federation provider, that can be queried by participating
        domains. The database contains mappings from phone numbers to domains,
        and is populated by each of the participating domains, often manually.
        Each domain implements an agreed-upon query interface that can be used
        to access the database when a number is called. Sometimes ENUM is used
        for this interface (called private ENUM), other times, a SIP
        redirection is used. Some federations also utilize private IP networks
        in order to address QoS problems. </t>

        <t>Private federations work, but they have one major limitation:
        scale. As the number of participating domains grows, several problems
        arise. Firstly, the size of the databases become difficult to manage. Secondly, the
        correctness of the database becomes an issue, since the odds of
        misconfigured numbers (either intentionally or accidentally)
        increases. As the membership grows further, the odds increase that
        malicious domains will be let in, introducing a source of spam and further
        problems. The owner of the federation can - and often does - assume
        responsibility for this, and can attempt to identify and shut down
        misbehaving participants. Indeed, as the size of the federations grow,
        the owner of the federation needs to spend increasing levels of
        capital on maintaining it. This often results in the owners 
        charging for membership, which can be a barrier to entry.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Key Requirements">
      <t>From the discussion on the problems of inter-domain federation and
      the solutions that have been attempted so far, several key requirements
      emerge:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="REQ-1:">The solution must allow for federation
          between any number of domains.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-2:">The solution must enable users in one domain to
          identify users in another domain through the use of their existing
          E.164 based phone numbers.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-3:">The solution must work with deployments that
          utilize any kind of endpoint, including non-IP phones connected
          through gateways, IP softphones and hardphones.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-4:">The solution must not require any change in
          user behavior. The devices and techniques that users have been using
          previously to make inter-domain calls must continue to work, but
          now result in inter-domain calls using IP.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-5:">The solution must work worldwide, for any
          domain anywhere.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-6:">The solution must not require any new
          services from any kind of centralized provider. A domain should be
          able to deploy equipment and
          connect to the federation without any interaction with or 
          authorization from a centralized provider.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-7:">The solution must not require any prior
          arrangement between domains in order to facilitate federation
          between those domains. Federation must occur opportunistically -
          connections established when they can be.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-8:">The solution must work for domains of any size
          - starting with a single phone up to the largest telecom operator with
          tens of millions of numbers.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-9:">The solution must have built-in mechanisms for
          preventing spam and DoS attacks. These mechanisms must be fully
          automated.</t>

          <t hangText="REQ-10:">The solution must not require any processing
          whatsoever by SIP or RTP intermediaries. It must be possible for a
          direct SIP connection to be established between participating
          domains.</t>
          
          <t hangText="REQ-11:"> The solution should adapt to VIPR call failures. The 
          solution should 
          allow the user to make calls using the   
          inter-domain calling mechanism used prior to the initial VIPR-enabled call. </t>
              
        </list></t>

     
    </section>

    <section title="Executive Overview">
      <t>Verification Involving PSTN Reachability (VIPR) is 
      aimed at solving the problems that have prevented large-scale
      Internet-based SIP federation of voice and video. VIPR solves these
      problems by creating a hybrid of three technologies - the PSTN itself, a
      Peer to Peer (P2P) network, and SIP. By using these three technologies together,
      VIPR enables an incrementally deployable solution to federation.</t>

      <section title="Key Properties">
        <t>VIPR has several important properties that enable it to solve the
        federation problem:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="Works With Numbers:">VIPR enables federation for
            existing PSTN phone numbers. It does not require users or administrators
            to know or configure email-style identifiers. It does not require
            the allocation of new numbers. It does not require a change in
            user behaviors. </t>

            <t hangText="Works with Existing Endpoints:">VIPR does not require
            any changes to endpoints. Consequently, it works with existing SIP
            endpoints and with non-IP endpoints connected through
            gateways.</t>

            <t hangText="Verified Mappings:">VIPR
            ensures that phone calls cannot be misrouted or numbers
            stolen. 
            The biggest issue in mapping from
            a phone number to a domain or IP address, is determining whether
            the mapping is correct - i.e., does the domain really own the given
            phone number? While solutions like ENUM have solved this problem
            by relying on centralized delegations of authorization, VIPR
            provides a secure mapping in a fully distributed way. </t>

            <t hangText="Worldwide:">VIPR works worldwide. Any domain that is
            connected to both the PSTN and the Internet can participate. 
            Since VIPR does not depend on availability of any
            regional services beyond IP and PSTN access - both of which are
            already available globally - VIPR itself is globally
            available.</t>

            <t hangText="Scalibility:">VIPR is scaleable. Any
            number of domains can participate.</t>

            <t hangText="Self-Scale:">VIPR self-scales. This means that the
            amount of computation, memory, and bandwidth that a domain must
            deploy scales in direct proportion to the size of their own user
            base.</t>

            <t hangText="Self-Learning:">VIPR is completely automated. A
            domain does not require configuration of any information about another
            domain. It does not require provisioning of IP addresses, domain names,
            certificates, phone number prefixes or routing rules. </t>

            <t hangText="Automated Anti-Spam">VIPR has a built-in
            mechanism for preventing SIP spam, which is specific to SIP. 
            It is fundamentally different from
            existing SIP anti-spam techniques which borrow from email <xref
            target="RFC5039"></xref>. This new technique is fully automated,
            and requires no configuration by administrators and no
            participation from end users.</t>

            <t hangText="Feature Velocity:">VIPR enables direct SIP
            connections between two domains seeking to federate. There are no
            SIP intermediaries of any sort between the two. This means that
            domains have no dependencies on intermediaries for deployment of
            new features.</t>

            <t hangText="Secure:"> Security is 
            a fundamental part of VIPR and cannot be disabled.</t>

            <t hangText="Reliable:">VIPR is reliable. Through its
            hybridization of the PSTN and the Internet, it ensures that
            calls always go through, even in cases of network failure or 
            limited IP connectivity. 
            </t>
          </list></t>

        <t>In order to achieve a solution with these properties, past assumptions about 
        how federations should work must be challenged. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Challenging Past Assumptions">
        <t>Two unstated assumptions of SIP federation are challenged by
        VIPR.</t>

        <t>The first assumption that federation solutions have made is this:
        <list style="empty">
            <t>The purpose of SIP federation is to eliminate the PSTN, and
            consequently, we cannot assume the PSTN itself as part of the
            solution.</t>
          </list> Though unstated, this assumption has clearly been part of
        the design of existing solutions. SIP federation based on email-style
        URIs, as defined in RFC 3261, doesn't utilize nor make mention of the
        PSTN. Solutions like ENUM, or private registries,
        also do not utilize nor
        make mention of the PSTN. However,
        such approaches ignore an incremental solution - a solution which
        utilizes the PSTN itself to solve the hard problems in SIP
        federation.</t>

        <t>There are many advantages to leveraging the PSTN. It reaches
        worldwide. It provides a global numbering translation service that
        maps phone numbers to circuits. It is highly reliable, and provides
        QoS. It has been built up over decades to achieve these goals. 
        Thus, building upon rather than replacing the PSTN, can provide
        the necessary functionality  
        once another assumption is challenged.</t>

        <t>
        This second assumption is: <list style="empty">
            <t>A federation solution must be the same as the final target
            federation architecture, and not just a step towards it.</t>
          </list> 
        SIP's email-style federation was a pure 'target architecture'. 
        ENUM was the same - a worldwide global DNS database
        with everyone's phone numbers providing open
        connectivity.</t>

        <t>Historically, technologies are more successful when they are
        incrementally deployable. As such, VIPR is very much focused on incremental 
        deployability. It
        discards the notion of perfect IP federation for a solution that
        federates most, but not all calls, by relying on the PSTN to fill in
        the gaps.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Technical Overview">
        <t>A high level view of the VIPR architecture with an example is shown in <xref
        target="fig-high-arch"></xref>.  
        The figure shows four different
        domains, example.com, example.net, example.org and example.edu, federated using VIPR
        technology. Each domain is connected to both the public Internet and
        to the traditional PSTN. For simplicity, the connection for the 
        call agents in example.org and 
        example.edu to the PSTN is not indicated in the diagram as that 
        interface is not relevant to the subsequent examples.</t>

        <figure anchor="fig-high-arch" title="High Level Architecture ">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

                      +-------+    +-------+
                      |  Call |    |  Call |
       example.org    | Agent |    | Agent |  example.edu
                      |       |    |       |                         
                      +-------+    +-------+
                          \           /
                           \         /        
                            \       / 
                             \     / 
                                |
                          //--------\\
                        |//          \\|
                        |   Internet   |
          +-------+     |\\          //|    +-------+
          |  Call |------ \\ _______//------|  Call |
  //\\    | Agent |                         | Agent |    //\\
  \  /    |       |                         |       |    \  /
   \/  ---|       |      +-----------+      |       |---- \/
  User    |       |======|           |======|       |    User
 Agent    +-------+      |    PSTN   |      +-------+   Agent 
          example.com    |           |    example.net
                         +-----------+         
                                 
       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

      
        <t>For purposes of explanation, it is easiest to think of each domain
        as having a single call agent which participates in the federation
        solution. The functionality 
        is decomposed into several
        sub-components, and this is discussed in more detail below. The call
        agent is connected to one or more user agents in the domain, and is
        responsible for routing calls, handling features, and processing call
        state. The call agent is stateful, and is aware of when calls start
        and stop. Additional detail for the
        functional components of this architecture are provided in 
        <xref target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-framework"/>.</t> 

        <t>Assume that all four domains have a 'fresh' installation of VIPR,
        and that domain example.net 'owns' +1 408 555 5xxx, a block of 1000 numbers
        allocated by its PSTN provider.</t>

        <t>The VIPR mechanism can be broken into four basic steps: storage of
        phone numbers, PSTN first call, validation and caching, and subsequent SIP
        call(s).</t>

        <section title="Storage of Phone Numbers">
          <t>The first step is that the call agents form a single, worldwide
          P2P network, using a VIPR specific usage 
          <xref target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-reload-usage"/> of 
          RELOAD <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"></xref> with
          a variant of the Chord algorithm.  This P2P network forms a 
          distributed hash table
          (DHT) running amongst all participating domains. A distributed hash
          table is like a simple database, allowing storage of key-value
          pairs, and lookup of objects by key. Unlike a normal hash table,
          which resides in the memory of a single computer, a distributed hash
          table is spread across all of the servers which make up the P2P
          network. In this case, it is spread across all of the domains
          participating in the VIPR federation.</t>

          <t>The problem solved by the variant of the Chord 
          algorithm  (and by other DHT algorithms), is
          an answer to the following: given that the desired operation is to
          read or write an object with key K, which node in the DHT is the box
          that currently stores the object with that key? The P2P SIP variant
          of the Chord algorithm provides an
          algorithm which routes read and write operations through
          nodes in the DHT until they eventually arrive at the right place.
          With Chord, this will take no more than log2N hops, where N is the
          number of nodes in the DHT. Consequently, for a DHT with 1024 nodes,
          10 hops are required in the worst case. For 2048, 11 hops. And so
          on. The logarithmic factor allows DHTs to achieve efficient scale
          and to provide a large amount of storage summed across all of the nodes that
          make up the DHT.</t>

          <t>This logarithmic hopping behavior also means that each node in
          the DHT does not need to establish a TCP/TLS connection to every
          other node. Rather, connections are established to a smaller subset
          - just log(N) of the nodes.</t>

          <t>In DHTs, each participating entity is identified by a Node-ID.
          The Node-ID is a 128 bit number, assigned randomly to each entity.
          They have no inherent semantic meaning; they are not like domain
          names or IP addresses.</t>

          <t>In the case of VIPR, each call agent is identified by one or more
          Node-IDs. For purposes of discussion, consider the case where the
          call agent has just one Node-ID. Each participating domain, including example.net
          in our example, uses the DHT to store a mapping from each phone
          number that it owns, to the domain's Node-ID. In the case of example.net, it
          would store 1000 entries into the DHT, each one being a mapping from
          one of its phone numbers, to the domain's Node-ID. Furthermore, when the
          mappings are stored, the mapping is actually from the SHA-1 hash of
          the phone number, to the Node-ID of the call agent which claims
          ownership of that number.</t>

          <t>For example, if the Node-ID of the call agent in domain example.net is
          0x1234 (a shorter 16 bit value to simplify discussion), the entries
          stored into the DHT by example.net would be:</t>

          <figure anchor="fig-high-arch2" title="DHT Contents">
            <artwork><![CDATA[

   Key             |    Value
----------------------------------
SHA1(+14085555000)  |   0x1234
SHA1(+14085555001)  |   0x1234
SHA1(+14085555002)  |   0x1234
.....
SHA1(+14085555999)  |   0x1234
]]></artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>It is important to note that the DHT does not contain phone
          numbers (it contains hashes of them), nor does it contain IP
          addresses or domain names. Instead, it is a mapping from the hash of
          a phone number (in E.164 format) to a Node-ID.</t>

          <t>example.net will store this mapping when it starts up, or when a new
          number is provisioned. The information is refreshed periodically by
          example.net. The actual server on which these mappings are stored depends
          on the variant of the Chord algorithm. Typically, the entries will be uniformly
          distributed amongst all of the call agents participating in the
          network.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="PSTN First Call">
          <t>At some point, a user agent (Alice) in example.com makes a call to +1 408 555
          5432, which is her colleague Bob. Even though both sides have VIPR,
          the call takes place over the plain old PSTN, per <xref target="pstncall"/>.
          Alice talks to Bob for
          a bit, and they hang up.</t>
          
          <figure anchor="pstncall" title="PSTN First Call">
          <artwork><![CDATA[

          +-------+                         +-------+
          |  Call |                         |  Call |
  //\\    | Agent |                         | Agent |    //\\
  \  /    |       |                         |       |    \  /
   \/  ---|       |      +-----------+      |       |---- \/
   Alice  |       |<=======<========>======>|       |    Bob
          +-------+      |    PSTN   |      +-------+
          example.com    |           |    example.net
                         +-----------+         
                                 
                                    
                               
                               ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          

          <t>At a random point in time after the call has completed, the call
          agent in example.com "wakes up" and says to itself, "that's interesting,
          someone in my domain called +1 408 555 5432, and it went over the
          PSTN. I wonder if that number is reachable over IP instead?". To
          make this determination, it hashes the called phone number, and
          looks it up in the DHT. It is important to note that this lookup is
          not at the time of an actual phone call - this lookup process
          happens outside of any phone call, and is a background process.</t>

          <t>The query for +1 408 555 5432 will traverse the DHT, and
          eventually arrive at the node that is responsible for storing the
          mapping for that number. Typically, that node will not be example.net, but
          rather one of the other nodes in the network (e.g., example.org).
          In many cases, the called number will not find a matching mapping in
          the DHT. This happens when the number that was dialed is not owned
          by a domain participating in VIPR. When that happens, example.com takes no
          further action. Next time there is another call to the same number,
          it will repeat the process and check once more whether the dialed
          number is in the DHT.</t>

          <t>In this case, there is a match in the DHT, and example.com learns the
          Node-ID of example.net. It then proceeds to the validation step per 
          <xref target="Validate-cache"/>. It is
          also possible that there are multiple matches in the DHT. This can
          happen if another domain - example.edu for example - also claims ownership
          of that number. When there are multiple matching results, example.com
          learns all of them, and performs the validation step with each.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="Validate-cache" title="Validation and Caching">
          <t>Why not just store the domain in the DHT, instead of the Node-ID?
          If the domain was stored in the DHT, once example.com performed the lookup, 
          it would immediately
          learn that the number maps to example.net, and could then make a direct
          SIP call next time.</t>

          <t>The main reason this doesn't work is security. The information in
          the DHT is completely untrusted. There is nothing so far that
          enables example.com to know that example.net does, in fact, own the phone number
          in question. Indeed, if multiple domains make a claim on the number,
          it has no way to know which one (if any) actually owns it.</t>

          <t>To address this critical problem, VIPR requires a 
          mechanism called phone number validation. Phone number validation is a key
          concept in VIPR. There are several models for this validation as detailed 
          in <xref target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-pvp"/>. 
          The essential idea is that example.com will connect to
          the example.net server, by asking the DHT to form a connection to example.net's
          Node-ID. Once connected, example.com demands proof of ownership of the
          phone number. This proof comes in the form of demonstrated knowledge
          of the previous PSTN call. When a call was placed from example.com to +1
          408 555 5432, the details of that call - including its caller ID,
          start time, and stop time, create a shared secret referred to as a "ticket", -
          information that is only known to entities that participated in the
          call. Thus, to obtain proof that example.net really owns the number in
          question, example.com will demand a knowledge proof - that example.net is aware
          of the details of the call. 
          A consequence of this is that the following property is
          maintained:</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
              <t>A domain can only call a specific number over SIP, if it had
              previously called that exact same number over the PSTN.</t>
            </list></t>
                      
          <t>This property is key in fighting spam and denial-of-service
          attacks. Because calling numbers on the PSTN costs money -
          especially international calls - VIPR creates a financial
          disincentive for spammers. For a spammer to ring every phone in a
          domain with a SIP call, it must have previously called every number
          in the domain with a PSTN call, and had a successfully completed
          call to each and every one of them. 
          <xref target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-sip-antispam"/>
          provides an 
          overview and further details on 
          the security mechanisms for VIPR for mitigation of SPAM. </t>         
          
          
          <t>There are a great many details required for this validation
          protocol to be secured.          
          For example, the mechanism needs to handle the fact that call start
          and stop times won't exactly match on both sides. It needs to deal
          with the fact that many calls start on the top of the hour. It needs
          to deal with the fact that caller ID is not often delivered, and
          when it is delivered, is not reliable. It needs to deal with the
          fact that example.com may in fact be the attacker, trying to use the
          validation protocol to extract the shared secret from example.net. All of
          this is, in fact, handled by the protocol. The protocol is based on
          the Secure Remote Password for TLS Authentication (SRP-TLS) <xref
          target="RFC5054"></xref>, and is described more fully in <xref
          target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-pvp"></xref>.</t>          
                   
          <t>Towards the end of the validation process, domains example.com and
          example.net had determined that each was, in fact in possession of the
          shared secret information about the prior PSTN call. However,
          neither side has any information about the domain names of the other
          side. </t>
          
          <t>At the end of the validation process, both example.com and example.net have
          been able to ascertain that the other side did in fact participate
          in the previous PSTN call. At that point, example.com sends its domain
          name to example.net as shown in <xref target="fig-ticket-step1"/>.</t>
          
           <figure anchor="fig-ticket-step1" title="Ticket Validation Step 1">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
            
            
            
                      +-------+    +-------+
                      |  Call |    |  Call |
       example.org    | Agent |    | Agent |  example.edu
                      |       |    |       |                         
                      +-------+    +-------+
                         \             /
+----------------------+  \           /
| Hi, I am example.com.|   \         /        
| How do I reach you?  |    \       / 
+--------------\-------+  //-------\\
                \        //         \\
             +===\======>========>========>=====+
             ^          |    Internet  |        |
             |          |              |        v
          +-------+     |\\          //|    +-------+
          |  Call |------ \\ _______//------|  Call |
  //\\    | Agent |                         | Agent |    //\\
  \  /    |       |                         |       |    \  /
   \/  ---|       |                         |       |---- \/
   Alice  |       |                         |       |    Bob
          +-------+                         +-------+
          example.com                      example.net
                         
            

  ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          
          <t>Next, the example.net domain generates the ticket. The ticket has three
          fundamental parts to it:</t>

          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>The phone number that was just validated - in this case, +1
              408 555 5432.</t>

              <t>The domain name that the originating side claims it has -
              example.com in this case.</t>

              <t>A signature generated by example.net, using a key known to itself
              only, over the other two pieces of information.</t>
            </list></t>

  
          
          <t>
          Then, example.net 
          sends to example.com - all over a secured channel - a SIP URI to use for
          routing calls to this number, and a ticket, as shown in 
          <xref target="fig-ticket-step2"/>. The ticket is a
          cryptographic object, opaque to example.com, but used by example.net to allow
          incoming SIP calls. It is similar in concept to kerberos tickets -
          it is a grant of access. In this case, it is a grant of access for
          example.com to call +1 408 555 5432, and only +1 408 555 5432.</t>
          

          <figure anchor="fig-ticket-step2" title="Ticket Validation Step 2">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
            
           
                      +-------+    +-------+
                      |  Call |    |  Call |
       example.org    | Agent |    | Agent |  example.edu
                      |       |    |       |                         
                      +-------+    +-------+
                         \             /
                          \           /    +------------------------+
                           \         /     | Here is your ticket    |    
                            \       /      | & SIP URI to reach Bob |
                          //-------\\      +----/-------------------+
                         //         \\         /
             +==========<========<========<===/=+
             |          |    Internet  |        ^
             v          |              |        |
          +-------+     |\\          //|    +-------+
          |  Call |------ \\ _______//------|  Call |
  //\\    | Agent |                         | Agent |    //\\
  \  /    |       |                         |       |    \  /
   \/  ---|       |                         |       |---- \/
   Alice  |       |                         |       |    Bob
          +-------+                         +-------+
          example.com                       example.net
                                
            

]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          
          
          
          
          
       
          <t>The example.com call agent receives the SIP URI and ticket, and stores
          both of them in an internal cache. This cache builds up slowly over
          time, containing the phone number, SIP URI, and ticket, for those
          numbers which are called by example.com and validated using VIPR. Because
          the cache entries are only built for numbers which have actually
          been called by users in the enterprise, the size of the cache
          self-scales. A call agent supporting only ten users will build up a
          cache proportional to the volume of numbers called by ten people,
          whereas a call agent supporting ten thousand users will build up a
          cache which is typically a thousand times larger.</t>
          
          <t> This cache, containing the phone number, SIP URI 
          and ticket will be accessed later when Alice (or another caller 
          from the same call agent) makes another call to 
          Bob, as detailed in
          <xref target="sipcall"/>.</t>
          
                  
                            
        </section>

        <section anchor="sipcall" title="SIP Call">
          <t>At some point in the future, another call is made to +1 408 555
          5432. The caller could be Alice, or it could be any other user
          attached to the same call agent. This time, the call agent notes
          that it has a cached entry (including the SIP URI and ticket) 
          for the number in question.   
          It is possible that there are multiple entries
          for a given number. For example, both an Enterprise and Service Provider
          may register the same number in the RELOAD distributed database.  
          It may also be possible to fork a call using the multiple entries . [Editor's 
          note: this requires further discussion as to whether we want to allow 
          multiple entries.]  </t>                           
       
          <t>The example.com call agent attempts to contact the SIP URI by
          establishing a TCP/TLS connection to the SIP URI it learned.
          If a
          connection cannot be made and there are no other cached entries for the
          number in question,
          the call agent proceeds with the call over the PSTN.
          This ensures that, in the event of an Internet failure or server
          failure, the call can still proceed. Assuming the connection is
          established, the example.com call agent sends a SIP INVITE to
          the terminating call agent, over this newly formed secure
          connection. The SIP INVITE request also contains the ticket,
          placed into a new SIP header field in the message.</t>

          <t>When the SIP INVITE arrives at the example.net call agent,
          the call agent can extract the ticket from the new SIP header field. 
          This ticket is an
          object, opaque to example.com, that was previously generated by the example.net
          call agent as 
          described in <xref target="Validate-cache"/>.
          example.net first verifies the signature over the
          ticket. Remember that the example.net agent is the one that generated the
          ticket in the first place; as such, it is in possession of the key
          required to validate the signature. Once validated, it performs two
          checks:</t>

          <t><list style="numbers">
              <t>It compares the phone number in the call setup request (the
              Request URI) against the phone number stored in the ticket.</t>

              <t>It compares the domain name of the calling domain, learned
              from the certificates in the mutual TLS exchange, against the
              domain name stored in the ticket.</t>
            </list></t>

          <t>If both match, the example.net call agent knows that the calling party
          is in fact the domain they claimed previously, and that they had in
          fact gone through the validation process successfully for the number
          in question. At this time, the call is now completed per normal SIP 
          processing. </t>
          
         </section>
      </section>
    </section>

 
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This section provides an
      overview of some of the key threats and how they are handled at a high level. Note that the detailed 
      security solutions to handle the threats are detailed in the other relevant VIPR documents
      as referenced in the sections below.</t>

      <section title="Attacks on the DHT">
        <t>Attackers could attempt to disrupt service through a variety of
        attacks on the DHT.</t>

        <t>Firstly, it must be noted that the DHT is never used at call setup
        time. It is accessed as a background task, solely to learn NEW numbers
        and SIP URIs that are not already known. If an
        attacker was able to completely destroy the P2P network, it would not result in a
        single call to fail. Furthermore, it would not cause calls to revert
        to the PSTN - calls to SIP URIs learned previously would still go over
        the IP network. The only impact to such a devastating attack is that
        a domain could not learn SIP URIs for new numbers, until the DHT is
        restored to service. This service failure is hard for users and
        administrators to even notice.</t>

        <t>That said, VIPR prevents many of these attacks. The DHT itself is
        secured using TLS - its usage is mandatory. Quota mechanisms are put
        into place that prevent an attacker from storing large amounts of data
        in the DHT as described in <xref target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-proportional-quota"/>. 
        Other attacks are prevented by mechanisms defined by
        RELOAD <xref target="I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"/> itself, and are not VIPR specific.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="theft" title="Theft of Phone Numbers">
        <t>A key security threat that VIPR is trying to address is the theft
        of phone numbers. In particular, a malicious domain could store, in
        the DHT, phone numbers that it does not own, in an attempt to steal
        calls targeted to those numbers. This attack is prevented by the core
        validation mechanism as described in <xref target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-pvp"/> , 
        which performs a proof of knowledge check to
        verify ownership of numbers.</t>

        <t>An attacker could try to claim numbers it doesn't own, which are
        claimed legitimately by other domains in the VIPR network. This attack
        is prevented as well. Each domain storing information into the DHT can
        never overwrite information stored by another domain. As a
        consequence, if two domains claim the same number, two records are
        stored in the DHT. An originating domain will validate against both,
        and only one will validate - the real owner.</t>

        <t>An attacker could actually own a phone number, use it for a while,
        validate with it, and build up a cache of routes at other domains.
        Then, it gives back the phone number to the PSTN provider, who
        allocates it to someone else. However, the attacker still claims
        ownership of the number, even though they no longer have it. This
        attack is prevented by expiring the learned routes after a while.
        Typically, operators do not re-assign a number for a few months, to
        allow out-of-service messages to be played to people that still have
        the old number. Thus, the TTL for cached routes is set to match the
        duration that carriers typically hold numbers.</t>

        <t>An attacker could advertise a lot of numbers, most of which are
        correct, some of which are not. VIPR prevents this by requiring each
        number to be validated individually.</t>

        <t>An attacker could make a call so they know the call details of the
        call they made and use this to forge a validation for that call. They
        could then try to convince other users, which would have to be in the
        same domain as the attacker, to trust this validation. This is
        mitigated by not sharing validations inside of domains where the users
        that can originate call from that domain are not trusted by the
        domain.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Spam">
        <t>Another serious concern is that attackers may try to launch SIP
        spam (also known as SPIT) calls into a domain. As described 
        in <xref target="Validate-cache"/> and as detailed in 
        <xref target="I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-sip-antispam"/>, VIPR prevents this by
        requiring that a domain make a PSTN call to a number before it will
        allow a SIP call to be accepted to that same number. This provides a
        financial disincentive to spammers. The current relatively high cost
        of international calling, and the presence of national do-not-call
        regulations, have prevented spam on the PSTN to a large degree. VIPR
        applies those same protections to SIP connections.</t>
       
        <t>VIPR still lowers the cost of communications, but
        it does so by amortizing that savings over a large number of calls.
        The costs of communications remain high for infrequent calls to many
        numbers, and become low for frequent calls to a smaller set of
        numbers. Since the former is more interesting to spammers, VIPR gears
        its cost incentives away from the spammers, and towards domains which
        collaborate frequently.</t>

        <t> It is important to note that VIPR does not completely address the
          spam problem. A large spamming clearing house organization could
          actually incur the costs of launching the PSTN calls to numbers, and
          then, in turn, act as a conduit allowing other spammers to launch
          their calls to those numbers for a fee. The clearinghouse would
          actually need to transit the signaling traffic (or, divulge the
          private keys to their domain name), which would incur some cost. As
          such, while this is not an impossible situation, the barrier is set
          reasonably high to start with - high enough that it is likely to
          deter spammers until it becomes a highly attractive target, at which
          point other mechanisms can be brought to bear. </t>
      </section>

      <section title="Eavesdropping">
        <t>Another class of attacks involves outsiders attempting to listen in
        on the calls that run over the Internet, or obtain information about
        the call through observation of signaling.</t>

        <t>All of these attacks are prevented by requiring the usage of SIP
        over TLS and SRTP. These are mandatory to use.</t>
      </section>
	  
	 <section anchor="malicious" title="Privacy Leakage and Malicious Servers">
	  
	  <t>
A further form of attack involves adding malicious VIPR servers to a widely
implemented (e.g., national or international) RELOAD overlay.  This attack
is specific to an uncontrolled RELOAD overlay, in which any individual or
enterprise could add their own VIPR server to the overlay without
authorization, verification or bias.
	  </t>
	  <t>
In this scenario, a malicious VIPR server could be used for analyzing
number registration information for the purpose of spying on called 
 numbers associated with various participating parties.  The likelihood
of this occurring on a large scale is small, because it might require a prohibitive (and easily-detectable) number
of VIPR servers to capture all of the number registrations of a region
under surveillance; however, more targeted attacks are feasible and should be recognized as a
potential security consideration.
	  </t>
	  <t>
This security breach can occur because all registrations are considered
equally untrusted, and they will be verified by establishing a TCP
connection between the VIPR server of the source of the call and the VIPR
server that stored the registration for a particular phone number.
Multiple pieces of identifying information are necessarily leaked in this verification process, 
but it is specifically easy to
identify the enterprise originating the TCP connection by comparing its
source address to public registry data (such as in-addr.arpa).  
</t><t>
For destination phone numbers using VIPR, the vulnerability arises because the
RELOAD overlay permits multiple entities to register for the same number. The VIPR
server at the source of the call may therefore discover multiple candidate registrations;
although malicious servers registering themselves will not possess the call details necessary to generate a shared secret,
they may learn sensitive information merely through participating in the verification process. 
While it is possible that the real owner of the number may be tried first and
prevent other registrations to be tried if successful, an attacker could register from multiple VIPR
servers in order to improve their chances of receiving a verification request. One could easily
imagine an attacker determined to learn who will call a particular number generating a large set
of registrations that would make it very unlikely for the authentic server to be selected first; with enough
such registrations it might effectively become a denial of service attack.
Note however that this problem is limited to server discovery: as soon as the
real owner sends a SIP route and ticket back, the malicious VIPR server
would no longer receive any information about the calls between the
enterprise and the destination number, with exception of the periodic
renewal of the ticket.
	  </t>
	  <t>The possible disclosed information includes more than the just the
connection verification.  Here is a list of potential leaked information:

	  <list><t>
	  If the malicious VIPR servers leverage a different VServiceId for each
registered phone number, the called number is always leaked.
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>
	  The called number is leaked during the validation process for both
methods A and B [draft-petithuguenin-vipr-pvp-04, Section 7.2.1, Section
7.2.2].
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>
	  For method A, the caller-ID is leaked (this is encrypted, but it is
possible to decrypt).
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>
	  For method B, a random time in the middle of the call is leaked.
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>
	  For method C, the rounded start and stop time of the call are leaked.
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>
	  The source IP address of the TCP connection for the PVP transaction is
always leaked.
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>
	  The addr_port in the AppAttachReq RELOAD message that was used to
establish the TCP connection is leaked. [draft-ietf-p2psip-base-24]
	  </t>
	  
	  <t>
	  The certificate of the signer of the AppAttachReq RELOAD message is
leaked.  While the certificate does not contain information about the
sender, but it always contains the Node-ID, which can always be resolved
to an IP address by using an Attach request.
	  </t></list></t>
	  
    </section>
</section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This specification does not require any actions from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks for review comments from Ken Fischer, Rob Maidhof, Michael
      Procter, Eric Burger, Richard Barnes and others. Thanks to Theo Zourzouvillys for pointing out the 5th
      theft of phone numbers attack as described in <xref target="theft"/> .</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

   
    </references>


    <references title="Informative References">

   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-p2psip-base"?>  
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-reload-usage"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-framework"?>
            
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-sip-antispam"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.jennings-vipr-vap"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-pvp"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.petithuguenin-vipr-proportional-quota"?>

       <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2543"?>
           
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3263"?>
      
      <reference anchor="E.164" target="">
        <front>
          <title>
            The International Public Telecommunication Number Plan          
          </title>

          <author>
            <organization>ITU-T</organization>                       
          </author>
          
          <date day="" month="May" year="1997" />
        </front>          
        
        <seriesInfo name='Recommendation' value='E.164' /> 
 
      </reference>
 
        
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5039"?>
       
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6116"?>
       
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5067"?>
        
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5054"?>
      <!-- Using the Secure Remote Password (SRP) Protocol for TLS -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6873" ?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.jones-insipid-session-id"?>
      
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-insipid-session-id-reqts"?>     
    </references>

    <section title="Changes since last version">
      <t>This section must be removed before publication as an RFC.</t>
      
      <t> Modifications between jennings-04 and jennings-03: </t>
      
      <t> <list style="numbers">  
      <t> Updating references to SIPCLF and Session ID (INSIPID) documents. </t>       
      
      </list>
      </t>

      <t> Modifications between jennings-03 and jennings-02: </t>
      
      <t> <list style="numbers">         
        <t> Reworded REQ -11 to clarify that in the case of call failures (i.e., IP calls),
         the system should fallback to inter-domain calling prior to VIPR.  </t> 
         <t> Deleted REQ-12 (Handover) since it's really not specific functionality provided by VIPR. </t>   
         <t> Moved some text from the -01 version in the Technical Overview section 
         back into the doc (not 
          sure why it was removed previously). </t>
        <t> Other editorial changes: </t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t> <list style="empty">  
        <t> - Added a Terminology section.</t>
        <t> - Clarified the use of the term "Call Agent".</t>
        <t> - Reworded discussion of email in section 2.2 (i.e., it's not useless). </t> 
        <t> - Either changed or removed altogether terms like "neat", "clever", 
        "incredible", "enormous" and 
        any text that read like marketing literature as much as possible.</t>
        <t> - Removed some of the more subjective and superfluous language - i.e.,
         condensed the text to be more concise (Section 5.2 and many others per 
         the previous change) </t>
        <t> - Deleted explicit reference to "SIP Trunking" as the statement didn't 
        introduce  additional information in that paragraph and the term is not 
        defined in this document. </t>
        <t> - and other minor editorial fixes.  </t>            
       </list>
      </t>
       
      <t> Modifications between jennings-02 and jennings-01:</t> 
      <t> <list style="numbers">
        <t> Sections 6,7,8 moved to new VIPR framework document. </t>
        <t> Editorial changes. </t>
        <t> Clarifications to re-enforce that the primary objective is not PSTN bypass but 
        rather to enable enhanced services such as video between domains.  Changed "VoIP" to
        "SIP" since the focus is not specifically voice. </t>
        <t> Added reference for new framework document. </t>
        <t> Section 5.3: Added references to other documents as appropriate - e.g., -pvp, -spam, etc.</t>
        <t> Moved validation diagrams and text (from 5.3.4) into Validation and 
        caching section (5.3.3).  </t>
        <t> Condensed discussion of spam in section 5.3.3 and updated SPAM section in 
        security section. </t>
      </list>
      </t>

 
      <t> Modifications between jennings-01 and rosenberg-04:</t>
      <t> <list style="symbols">
       <t> Not specified. </t>
       </list>
      </t>  
      
      <t> Modifications between rosenberg-04 and rosenberg-03 </t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Nits.</t>

            <t>Shorter I-Ds references.</t>

            <t>Changed phone numbers to follow E.123 presentation.</t>

            <t>Expanded P2P initialisms.</t>

            <t>Uses +1 408 555 prefix for phone numbers in examples.</t>
          </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
