<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-dbenham-webrtc-videomti-01" ipr="trust200902"
     updates="">
  <?rfc toc="yes"?>

  <?rfc tocdepth="4"?>

  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>

  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

  <!-- for I-D stage only -->

  <?rfc strict="no" ?>

  <!-- as we have no 'Security Considerations' in isolation-->

  <?rfc comments="yes" ?>

  <?rfc inline="no" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="AVC for RTCweb MTI">H.264/AVC as Mandatory-to-Implement
    Video Codec for RTCweb</title>

    <author fullname="David Benham" initials="D" surname="Benham">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose, CA 95134</city>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>dbenham@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <author fullname="Cullen" initials="C" surname="Cullen Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose, CA 95134</city>

          <country>United States</country>
        </postal>

        <email>fluffy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="David Singer" initials="D" surname="Singer">
      <organization>Apple</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
         
        </postal>

        <email>singer@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Krasimir Kolarov" initials="K" surname="Kolarov">
      <organization>Apple</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
         
        </postal>

        <email>kolarov@apple.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>



    <date/>

    <area>Real-time Applications and Infrastructure</area>

    <workgroup>RTCweb Working Group</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo proposes that H.264/AVC be selected as the
      mandatory-to-implement (MTI) video codec for RTCweb due to is Adoption
      Advantage, Quality-Power-Bandwidth advantage, Hardware Acceleration
      Advantage and Well-established IPR Status.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This memo offers a proposal that H.264/AVC be selected as the
      mandatory-to-implement (MTI) video codec for RTCweb. This document
      asserts that the constrained baseline profile is the likely best choice
      and uses it to make certain points. However, the author(s) are open to
      assertions that other H.264/AVC profile(s) should be additionally
      mandated or recommended.</t>

      <t>This document is not intended for publication as an RFC.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in RFC2119>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Adoption" title="H.264/AVC Adoption Advantage ">
      <t>H.264/AVC is widely used for enterprise videoconferencing equipment
      and services. High-definition (HD), web videoconferencing commonly uses
      H.264/AVC as well, including Skype.</t>

      <t>H.264/AVC is becoming the de-facto standard for the Mobile web and
      3GPP has recommended the H.264/AVC <xref target="AVC01"></xref> codec
      along with the mandatory H.263. Apple’s iOS, Google's Android, RIM’s
      Blackberry and Ericsson’s mobile device platforms all support
      H.264/AVC.</t>

      <t>Web (entertainment) video is dominated by H.264/AVC, and increasingly
      “multi-screen/BYOD” video services from cable companies and telco’s are
      using H.264/AVC over their private web video networks</t>

      <t>Thus, HTML5 browsers will likely need to have the H.264/AVC codec
      regardless to remain popular. Internet Explorer and Safari appear to be
      including H.264/AVC in the set of codecs they ship regardless of the
      RTCweb video codec MTI decision. And Google’s Chrome continues shipping
      with H.264/AVC today.</t>

      <t>We assert that the lack of clearly indicating that H.264/AVC was the
      mandatory video codec for HTML5’s video tag has created uncertainty and
      increased costs for those deploying sites or developing applications
      trying to cover multiple possible codecs instead. </t>

      <t>Mandating the H.264/AVC codec for RTCweb is in the best interest of
      rapid adoption given it is already pervasive deployed and used in
      real-time communications and web video applications. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Quality-Power-Bandwidth"
             title="H.264/AVC has the Quality-Power-Bandwidth advantage">
      <t>First, we believe that mobile devices will be important to the
      success of RTCweb going forward. They generally have slower CPUs than
      desktop computers and maximizing battery life is extremely important.
      </t>

      <t>Second, we assert that the three (3) most important factors to
      analyze in that context are a) the user experience or perceptual quality
      of the resultant video images, b) the amount of compute or CPU power
      applied to do the compression - this correlates with electrical power
      consumption, and c) the amount of bandwidth available or consumed. All
      three factors must be considered together as they are interrelated. </t>

      <t>For a given bitrate, a codec can improve the quality by doing more
      computation, but that will drain power quicker. While 4G/LTE brings more
      bandwidth to the equation, error properties of the medium and/or mobile
      data transmission costs will still put pressure on implementers to
      minimize bandwidth utilized by RTCweb streams. Throwing bandwidth at the
      problem is not a good assumption to improve quality while keeping CPU
      power constant.</t>

      <t>We quickly captured examples of leading H.264/AVC and VP8 products on
      popular mobile and desktop platforms and came to the conclusion that
      H.264 looks better than VP8 when both are run on same platform at the
      same bitrates.</t>

      <t>It is very hard in making tests to try and decide what parameters to
      use for codecs in a way that does not bias tests. So instead, we choose
      the "best in class" products that we could find to demonstrate
      performance comparisons.</t>

      <t>Captures of Mobile Tests;</t>


      <t>FaceTime using H.264 on an iPhone to linphone on a fast desktop PC.
     http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/facetime.mov </t>


      <t>Bria using VP8 on iPhone to linphone on a fast desktop PC. 
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/iphone-vp8-vs-iphone-264.mov </t>

      <t>Bria using VP8 on Galaxy Nexus to linphone on a fast desktop PC.
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/galaxy-nexus.mov </t>

      <t>Shown side-by-side, Bria using VP8 on iPhone (left) and FaceTime with
      H.264/AVC on iPhone (right), going to linphone and FaceTime.
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/iphone-vp8-vs-iphone-264.mov </t>

      <t>Captures of Desktop-only Tests;</t>

      <t>FaceTime H.264/AVC from a fast notebook computer to fast desktop.
      
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/facetime-264-desktop.mov </t>

      <t>-or-
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/facetime-264-desktop.webm </t>

      <t>Chrome with VP8 from same fast notebook computer to same fast
      desktop.
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/chrome-vp8-desktop.mov </t>

      <t>-or-
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/chrome-vp8-desktop.webm </t>

      <t>Two fast notebook computers - one running Chrome and the other
      running Fictive - both sending to the same desktop computer shown side
      by side.
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/chrome_and_factime_desktop.mov></t>

      <t>-or-
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/17089001/video-samples/chrome_and_factime_desktop.webm</t>


      <t>The tests and resultant captures were done on a fast wireless network
      with no other traffic on the wireless network, with the exception of the
      side by side demo. For the sides by side demo above, both devices were
      on the same WiFi network but did not seem to be having any losses or
      coming close to filling the network. The results in the side by side
      seemed to be the same as when there were run independently so we do not
      believe that having them both on the same network impacted results. </t>

      <t>Of course, these results do not preclude implementations improving in
      the future, but this gives some idea of the current state of the art.
      </t>

      <t>Our conclusion is that H.264/AVC is best at delivering on the
      Quality-Power-Bandwidth optimization. </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="HardwareAcceleration"
             title="Hardware Acceleration Advantage">
      <t>H.264/AVC has a several year head start on hardware/DSP optimization
      and is already deployed pervasively. For handheld mobile phones,
      hardware acceleration is a must to maximize Quality-Power-Bandwidth.
      </t>

      <t>H.264/AVC hardware is already incredibly inexpensive. Some of the low
      end consumer cameras will record H.264/AVC video, such as this sub-100
      US dollar (&lt;$100) Powershot A810 from Cannon<xref
      target="AVC07">.</xref></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IPRstatus"
             title="Well-Established IPR Status for H.264/AVC">
      <section anchor="DisclosedPatents"
               title="Disclosed and Publicly Available Lists of Patents">
        <t>As typical with many standards bodies, the joint work of ITU/MPEG
        that produced H.264/AVC has a common patent policy requiring
        disclosure by participants and third parties of any known patents or
        patent applications that may be essential to implement specifications
        in development. These can be downloaded in spreadsheet format <xref
        target="AVC02"></xref>. The policy goes on to ask contributors to
        pre-agree to either RAND (reasonable &amp; non-discriminatory, but may
        not be free) or royalty-free licensing of their own company’s patents,
        with or without reciprocal requirements. There is some anecdotal
        evidence to suggest US courts consider such disclosure requirements
        <xref target="AVC03"> </xref> in patent lawsuit decisions. </t>

        <t>While all that alone doesn’t guarantee 100% visibility of all
        possible essential patent claims, H.264/AVC was finished in late 2003
        and has been commercially shipping at scale for 6-7 years or more
        which should have brought to light any other patent holders interested
        in enforcing or collecting on their essential patents.</t>

        <t>Over 300 patents (more if counting multiple jurisdictions) covering
        mechanisms spanning several of AVC’s profiles are licensed via the
        MPEG LA H.264/AVC licensing program and are publicly listed <xref
        target="AVC04"></xref>.</t>

        <t>The risk of an unknown, essential patent appearing at this point
        should be comparatively low, which would be a benefit to selecting a
        H.264/AVC profile as the mandatory codec.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="DisclosedPatents2"
               title="Royalty Free for Innovation, Low-volume shipments">
        <t>To paraphrase, the MPEG LA license <xref target="AVC05"></xref>
        does allow up to 100K units per year, per legal entity/company (type
        “a” sublicensees in MPEG LA’s definition), to be shipped for zero ($0)
        royalty cost. This should be adequate for many RTCweb innovators or
        start-ups to try out new implementations on a large set of users
        before incurring any patent royalty costs, a benefit to selecting a
        H.264/AVC profile as the mandatory codec.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="HigherTools"
               title="Higher H.264/AVC Profile Tools Bundled">
        <t>It should be noted that when one licenses the MPEG LA H.264/AVC
        pool [AVC04], patents for higher profile tools – such as CABAC, 8x8 - are
        bundled in with those required for the constrained baseline profile.
        Thus, these could optionally be used by RTCweb implementers to achieve
        even greater performance or efficiencies than using H.264 constrained
        baseline alone, a benefit to selecting H.264/AVC and RTCweb could also
        go as far as recommending those higher profiles.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="FutureRF" title="Future IPR Status Consideration">
        <t>For additional informative purposes, the MPEG/IEC/ISO made a call
        for a royalty-free video coding solution for the Internet. As of its
        98th meeting, two tracks forward are being pursued; one of which is
        based on the H.264/AVC constrained baseline profile <xref
        target="AVC06"></xref>. MPEG is presently collecting patent
        licensing declarations that would include patent holder’s royalty
        expectations unbundled from other higher profile mechanisms. Should
        this effort result in a royalty-free constrained baseline profile,
        this would benefit RTCweb in the future if H.264/AVC is selected as
        mandatory today.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="WhatisVP8status"
             title="Questions about IPR Status of VP8">
      <t>For the purposes of further illustrating the benefits of the
      well-known IPR status of H.264/AVC, what follows are some comparisons to
      the unknowns that surround VP8 as of the writing of this contribution.
      Information that resolves the open questions below is welcomed. </t>

      <t>First, Google should be commended for offering their essential
      patents on VP8 royalty-free. However, other patent holders –- including
      ones not licensees of VP8/WebM -- may exist as suggested by all the
      respondents to MPEG LA’s call for a VP8 essential patent pool. Also, VP8
      was not developed openly in a standards body and thus subjected to the
      prescribed essential patent disclosures, etc.</t>

      <t>Second, others have previously advocated that the lack of lawsuits
      against shipping VP8 implementations to date means all is ok. VP8 has
      been shipping a shorter time compared to H.264/AVC and the finite number
      of companies that have shipped it to date may have, for example,
      sufficiently large patent portfolios themselves to have discouraged
      others from starting such a VP8 lawsuit against them. Bottom line is
      that it isn’t a good argument that no prior lawsuits are an implicit
      indication of low risk to future patent lawsuit for VP8.</t>

<texttable anchor="table_1" title="Comparison of H.264/AVC & VP8 IPR Status Impacting Features">
   <ttcol align='center'>Attribute</ttcol>
   <ttcol align='center'>AVC</ttcol>
   <ttcol align='center'>VP8</ttcol>
   <c>Developed Openly in Standards Body</c>
   <c>Yes</c>
   <c>No</c>

<c> - </c><c> </c><c> </c>

   <c>Required Patent Disclosures and/or predeclared RAND or similar licensing promise</c>
   <c>Yes</c>
   <c>No</c>

<c> - </c><c> </c><c> </c>

   <c>Open Source implementation</c>
   <c>Yes</c>
   <c>Yes</c>

<c> - </c><c> </c><c> </c>

   <c>Patent Royalties</c>
   <c>Yes for >100KU per yr</c>
   <c>None Known (*)</c>
</texttable>

      <t>(*) A dozen or so companies responded to MPEG LA’s call for essential
      patents on VP8, but a license for that has not been published and fees
      that may be asked for in the future is unknown. </t>

      <t>As suggested by Table 1, sufficient time and open, industry
      development along with the prescribed patent disclosures is beneficial
      to be more certain of the risks with shipping the chosen mandatory
      codec.</t>

      <t>Not having the benefit of a longer deployment duration and open,
      industry development for VP8, the following questions result;</t>

      <t><list style="empty">
          <t>(a) Like MPEG/IEC/ISO, can Google list the present patents
          covered in its VP8 license (of course it is noted that any future
          Google owned essential patents are supposed to be included too)?</t>

          <t>(b) Does Google, or anyone else involved in any patent analysis,
          know of any third-parties with viable essential patent claims on
          VP8? c) If any in (b), are they not a concern? Why? </t>

          <t>(c) If any in (b), are they not a concern? Why?</t>

          <t>(d) If Google is certain there is no concern regarding (b) &amp;
          (c), can Google provide some assurance (such as indemnification) to
          the VP8 licensees and thus indirectly assuring the RTCweb working
          group?</t>
        </list></t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>None.</t>
    </section>

<!--
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thank you to --blank-- for their valuable contributions.</t>
    </section>
-->

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc ?>

      <reference anchor="AVC01"
                 target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/26235.htm">
        <front>
          <title>Packet switched conversational multimedia applications;
          Default codecs</title>

          <author initials="TS 26.235" surname="3GPP"/>

          <date month="" year="2008"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="AVC02"
                 target="http://www.iso.org/iso/standards_development/patents">
        <front>
          <title>ISO Standards and Patent\s</title>

          <author initials="" surname="ISO"/>

          <date month="April" year="2006"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="AVC03"
                 target="http://caselaw.findlaw.com/us-federal-circuit/1150919.html">
        <front>
          <title>QUALCOMM INCORPORATED v. BROADCOM CORPORATION</title>

          <author initials="" surname="US Federal Court"/>

          <date month="December" year="2008"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="AVC04"
                 target="http://www.mpegla.com/main/programs/avc/Documents/avc-att1.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>MPEG LA H.264 AVC Patent Pool – Attachment 1</title>

          <author initials="" surname="MPEG LA"/>

          <date month="August" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="AVC05"
                 target="http://www.mpegla.com/main/programs/avc/Documents/AVC_TermsSummary.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>SUMMARY OF AVC/H.264 LICENSE TERMS</title>

          <author initials="" surname="MPEG LA"/>

          <date month="" year="unknown"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="AVC06"
                 target="http://mpeg.chiariglione.org/working_documents/mpeg-04/part29/WVC.zip">
        <front>
          <title>Working Draft 2 of ISO/IEC 14496-29 Web Video Coding</title>

          <author initials="ISO" surname="MPEG"/>

          <date month="" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="AVC07"
                 target="http://www.usa.canon.com/cusa/consumer/products/cameras/digital_cameras/powershot_a810">
        <front>
          <title>Powershot A810 Specifications</title>

          <author initials="" surname="Cannon Inc"/>

          <date month="" year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
