<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- comment -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?> 

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-nandakumar-mmusic-rtcweb-grouping" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
<front>
    <title abbrev="SSRC Group Simulcast">
		SSRC Group Based Simulcast Signaling
	</title>
	 <author fullname="Suhas Nandakumar" initials="S." surname="Nandakumar">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>snandaku@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
     <author fullname="Cullen Jennings" initials="C." surname="Jennings">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 West Tasman Drive</street>

          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone>+1 408 421-9990</phone>

        <email>fluffy@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <date year="2013" month="July" day="14" />
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>MMUSIC Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>RTP</keyword>
    <keyword>SDP</keyword>
	<keyword>Multiplexing</keyword>
    <keyword>RTCWEB</keyword>
    <keyword>WEB</keyword>
    <keyword>Browser</keyword>

    <abstract>
		<t>
			 In some applications it may be necessary to send multiple media encodings 
			 corresponding to a media source with in independent RTP media streams. 
			 This is called Simulcast. This document discusses a framework for describing
			 simulcast media streams in SDP and also defines semantics to express 
			 relationship amongst them. The semantics defined in this document are to 
			 be used with the source specific grouping framework defined in 
			the <xref target="RFC5576"/>
		</t>
    </abstract>
</front>

<middle>
<section title="Terminology" toc="default">
		<t>
			The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", 
			"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be 
			interpreted as described in RFC 2119  <xref target="RFC2119" pageno="false" 
			format="default"/>.
		</t>
		<t>
		 Capture Device:
   			The physical source of stream of media data of one type such as
   			camera or microphone.
        </t>
        <t>
		 Media Source:
   			A Media Source logically defines the source of a raw stream of media
   			data as generated either by a single capture device or by a
   			conceptual source.  A Media Source represents an Audio Source or a
   			Video Source.
        </t>
        <t>
	     Media Encoding:
  			A particular encoding applied to the media data from a media source through
  			the choice of sampling, bit-rate and other codec configuration parameters.
        </t> 
        <t>
         Media Stream:
   			Media from a Media Source is encoded and packetized to produce one or
   			more Media Streams representing a sequence of RTP packets.
        </t>
   		<t>
		 RTP Source:
  			Same as Media Stream.
  		</t>
  		<t>
		 RTP Session:
  			 An RTP session is an association among a group of participants
   			communicating with RTP.  It is a group communications channel which
   			can potentially carry a number of Media Streams.  Within an RTP
   			session, every participant finds out meta-data and control
   			information (over RTCP) about all the Media Streams in the RTP
   			session.  The bandwidth of the RTCP control channel is shared within
   			an RTP Session.
   		</t>	
	</section>

    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <t>
        Simulcast refers to taking media from a single media capture (e.g., a camera), 
        and encoding it multiple times at different resolutions and / or frame rates.
        For example, a device with a single HD camera may send one version of the 
        video at full HD resolution, and a second version encoded at a low resolution. 
        This would allow a video conferencing bridge to be able to send the 
        high resolution copy to some destination and low resolution copy to 
        other destinations without having to recode the video at the 
        conference bridge.
      </t>
	   <t>	
		In any application that needs to send multiple encodings, there is a 
		potential need for simulcast. The purpose of this document is to discuss 
		suitable signaling solution in SDP for describing and negotiating 
		simulcast streams, within the context on Real Time Transport Protocol.
       </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Solution Overview" toc="default">
      <t>
        The source-attribute specification <xref target="RFC5576"/> provides mechanisms 
        describing Real-Time Protocol (RTP) <xref target="RFC3550"/>  sources, 
        identified by their synchronization source (SSRC) identifier, 
        in the Session Description Protocol (SDP) <xref target="RFC4566"/>, 
        to associate attributes with these sources, and to express relationships 
        among individual sources.
      </t>
      <t>
        To describe and negotiate simulcast streams with in SDP for a given media source, 
        the following framework is been proposed:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t> 
            Each physical media source is represented by its own unique m-line. 
            This is a strict one-to-one mapping; a single media source device cannot
            be spread across several m-lines, nor may a single m-line represent multiple 
            media sources.
          </t>
          <t>  
            Each simulcast media stream is marked with an a=ssrc attribute to correlate
            it with its RTP Packets
          </t>
          <t>
            A new SSRC Grouping semantic is proposed to express the simulcast 
            relationship between the media streams.
          </t> 
          <t>
             In the absence of the above grouping semantic, multiple SSRCs in a single m-line 
             are interpreted as alternate sources for the same media source.
          </t>
          <t>
             For multi-resolution simulcast, <xref target="RFC6236"/>  imageattr is 
             proposed for  a=ssrc attribute line, to specify send multiple resolutions, 
             for example.
           </t>
        </list> 
      </t>
      <t>
      Providing explicit resolutions on a per-SSRC basis for SIMULCAST groupings 
      allows an intermediary (such as a Media Translator <xref target="RFC5117"/>) 
      to be able to select an appropriate SIMULCAST layer without inspecting 
      the media stream, which could otherwise require decrypting and possibly 
      partially decoding media packets.
      </t>
      </section>
      <section title="imageattr for a=ssrc attribute" toc="default">
        <t>
          This document extends a=ssrc attribute <xref target="RFC5576"/> by 
          introducing <xref target="RFC6236"/> imageattr enabling specification of
          multi-resolution simulcast streams for a give media source.
        </t>
      </section>
       <section title="The SIMUCAST ssrc-group attribute" toc="default">
        <t>
          This document also extends <xref target="RFC5576"/> SSRC Grouping Framework semantics
          (a=ssrc-group) to indicate relationship between the simulcast media streams 
          for a given media source. A semantic called "SIMULCAST" is defined to 
          achieve this purpose.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="SDP Examples" toc="default">
         <t>
          The example SDP in Figure 1 shows simulcast encoding with the use of 
          different codec-specific parameters using two different payload types for a 
          camera source. It also describes different resolutions for each encoded
          simulcast media stream. The "SIMULCAST"  SSRC grouping semantic is included to 
          signal the relationship.
         </t> 
        <figure title="Figure 1">
         <artwork><![CDATA[
m=video 62537 RTP/SAVPF 96 97 
a=rtpmap:96 VP8/90000
a=rtpmap:97 VP8/90000
a=sendrecv
a=ssrc:29154
a=imageattr:96  [x=1280,y=720]       //Stream 1
a=fmtp:96 max-fr=30;max-fs=3600
a=ssrc:47182
a=imageattr:97 [x=640,y=360]         //Stream 2 
a=fmtp:97 max-fr=15;max-fs=880
a=ssrc-group:SIMULCAST 29154 47182  
]]></artwork>
      </figure> 
   
       <t>
         The SDP example in Figure 2, advertises simulcast of 2 video sources 
         corresponding to 2 cameras, each at 2 resolutions.
        </t> 
 <figure title="Figure 2">
         <artwork><![CDATA[
m=video 62537 RTP/SAVPF 96 97   //Camera 1
a=rtpmap:96 VP8/90000
a=rtpmap:97 VP8/90000
a=sendrecv
a=ssrc:11111
a=ssrc:22222
a=imageattr:96 [x=1280,y=720]
a=fmtp:96 max-fr=30;max-fs=3600
a=imageattr:97 [x=640,y=360]
a=fmtp:97 max-fr=15;max-fs=880
a=ssrc-group:SIMULCAST 29154 47182  

m=video 54890 RTP/SAVPF 96 97  //Camera 2 
a=rtpmap:96 H264/90000
a=rtpmap:97 H264/90000
a=sendrecv
a=ssrc:33333
a=ssrc:44444
a=fmtp:96 profile-level-id=4d0028;packetization-mode=1;max-fr=30
a=fmtp:97 profile-level-id=4d0028;packetization-mode=1;max-fr=15
a=ssrc-group:SIMULCAST 33333 44444
]]></artwork>
      </figure> 
   
     <t>
      The SDP example in Figure 3 shows multi-resolution source capable of sending
      and receiving 2 resolutions.
    </t>
    <figure title="Figure 3">
         <artwork><![CDATA[
m=video 62537 RTP/SAVPF 96
a=rtpmap:96 VP8/90000
a=sendrecv
a=ssrc:11111 imageattr:96 send [x=1280,y=720]   //resolution 1
a=ssrc:22222 imageattr:96 send [x=640,y=480]    //resolution 2
a=imageattr:96 recv [x=640, y=480] [x=320,y=240] //recv capability
a=ssrc-group:SIMULCAST 111111 22222
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </section>
     
     
	<section title="Offer/Answer Consideration">
	  <t>
	     The Offer/Answer model for this specification adheres to the model as applicable
	     to Source-Specific Media SDP attributes and its extensions.
	   </t>
	</section>	
    <section title="IANA Considerations" toc="default">
		<t>
		</t>
    </section>
		
    <section anchor="sec-acks" title="Acknowledgements" toc="default">
    </section>

</middle>

<back>
    <references title="Normative References">
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>		
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3264"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4566"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5888"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5576"?>
		<?rfc include="reference.RFC.6236"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5117"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3550"?>
        <?rfc include="reference.I-D.lennox-mmusic-sdp-source-selection"?>
        
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
